[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert blumen I have with me
today James Strong James is a cloud
native and infrastructure engineer
he is a maintainer on the kubernetes
ingr enginex project and is currently a
Senior Solutions architect at
isovalent James is the co-author with
Valerie Lacy of the book networking and
kubernetes a layered approach published
by
O'Reilly and that will be the subject of
our conversation today James welcome to
software engineering radio I am super
excited to be here Robert I love talking
about networking I love going as deep as
possible it's also be interesting to
talk about networking without diagram so
we'll see how well we can describe
things together yeah that is a common
challenge that we face on software
engineering radio unless there's
anything else you'd like to say about
your background we can Dive Right In
that's a pretty good wrap up I say that
now and I we've going to talk a lot
about software engineering and a lot of
the times these days I'm talking to a
lot of network Engineers who are getting
just
into kubernetes and Cloud native space
so a lot of those questions I had the
same when I started I thought I wanted
to be a network engineer I was on the
path to try to get a ccie the cloud just
came around I was like this is very
interesting I should have I went around
working with that for a little while and
then kubernetes popped up as well to try
to be this operating system for the data
center all of those conversations like
the abstraction all of that and I just
slowly migrated to doing the kubernetes
piece just because it was infrastructure
it was networking it was software it was
a really good cross-section of all of
those things so yeah that was a real
quick overview of just I've been through
that transition and hopefully I can have
a intelligent conversation about that
and I answered a lot of questions last
week in cubec con about how to go from
being a network engineer to working on
kubernetes networking your career path
is relevant to our audience and our
podcast the podcast software engineering
radio has been around for about 20 years
when it started we really focused a lot
on the writing code aspect of software
engineering but over time the topics
that we talk about have broadened to
include many things in networking and
security which are now considered normal
for a software engineer to know about
and use in their job I think you have a
great background to talk about this
topic I think everyone should understand
how the network works know as a saying
in networking it's guilty till proven
innocent so if we can skip that step and
just have a conversation about
performance issues or other things like
that that'd be great we'll be talking
about the kubernetes network we have
some existing content on kubernetes in
particular 445 on ebpf and 586 on
vpc's and a bunch of other kubernetes
topics in the archive but nothing
specifically about the network I'm going
to say to introduce this when I started
looking at kubernetes it differs from
other distributed systems many
distributed systems you have some hosts
you have a network you run the service
on the hosts and they use the host
Network that is not how kubernetes Works
what is the big difference I would like
to challenge that assumption because I
hear that a lot where again having this
conversation with folks who are just
getting into kubernetes one of the big
things that I've learned
while going through this and
troubleshooting helping doing you know
standing up kubernetes clusters and
migrating applications to kubernetes is
that Linux networking it's still if you
have a Linux networking background you
understand how interfaces work how IP
addresses get signed how routing works
you just need to learn how kubernetes
talks about it from that perspective so
you're still setting up network
interfaces so there are abstractions and
software that do it for you instead of
having someone else do it so you're not
putting in a ticket to get an IP address
and get a CIS admin to set up a network
interface there's software that does it
for you and one of those abstractions
and I'm sure we'll talk about this more
is the container network interface so
kubernetes relies on the routing of the
underlying hosts as well as the software
the container network interface to set
up the networking for us
kubernetes doesn't know about the
underlying networking from that
perspective so it expects that nodes can
talk to each other so there are some
underlying expectations and assumptions
and then there's also just again it is
just Linux networking from that
perspective want talk at a high level I
start out with my initial premise that
kubernetes is different than a standard
distributed system and you're pushing
back on that so maybe if you could bear
with me a bit I'm wrong but why did I
think that and you explain why I'm wrong
but why is there something about that
that is at least partially true or how
is kubernetes networking not got more
layers to it than the flat distributed
system that I described I would say that
I think we're both right is that it is
still just Linux but there are layers of
abstraction on it so when kubernetes
starts a pod and says I need a pod there
are several things that happen and we
can walk through that and maybe go
specifically into the networking side of
that so the lowest common denominator
for a container or for an application is
a pod and a pod is a collection of
containers so you can have multiple
containers running in there besides just
your specific application well when that
starts up it needs a control group and a
name space control groups are
controlling for the resources of the
container so you're looking at like CPU
limits and things like that memory
limits that's are all implemented in the
control groups and then Nam spaces names
spaces allow us to have that abstraction
where a pod looks like it is inside of
its own I hate to say it virtual space
so you'll have things like a network
name space that's differentiates it
between the network stack between the
host and the Pod running on it this is
why you can have a pod running on Port
80 inside its own Network namespace and
it won't conflict with other pods
running Port 80 as well because normally
on a host the network can only have one
process running on Port 80 so the
network namespace is what allows us to
do that there are other namespaces as
well the process ID namespace the user
ID the user name space there's a couple
more I think there's six or seven I may
be wrong with that number but the one
we're specifically concerned about is
the network namespace and that's what
allows us to have the port s running on
specific ports that don't conflict those
also need to get wired up to the
traditional physical Network that we
think about or just the traditional
Network I mean vpcs are also you you've
talked about those vpcs also aren't
physical networks those are virtual
networks running on top of physical
networks so there's lots of layers of
distraction all right you've introduced
a bunch of things that I I want to cover
all those things in sure more detail you
are going into names spaces that is
something I want to come back to I want
to really understand what it does and
why and then go more into how I think
one of the key points you made is that
when the Pod boots up and it's in its
own namespace it can connect to Port 80
or 443 or whatever its preferred Port
why is that important in the kubernetes
world well we've talked about it's a
distributed system so you could be
running thousands of PODS that are
running on Port 80 443 8080 so in order
to be able to have that density and have
pods you'll have four or five pods
possibly running on that Port so
kubernetes does that for you from the
abstraction and it does that a
translation for you so it manages the
mapping so the Pod thinks it's running
on Port 80 but on the host Network it
could be running on on you know
32368 okay so that's important because
one of the key value ads of kubernetes
is enables efficient use of your compute
resources you could buy or lease
whatever VMS based on the overall value
of that VM and then you could put many
different pods on that VM so you could
efficiently use all the compute that
you're paying for versus is otherwise
you'd be faced with a decision of either
I'm going to have one pod per VM or I'm
only going to have one service that can
use port 80 on a given VM this approach
it overcomes that limit and allows
efficient packing is that more or less
going in the right direction yeah that
is one of the use cases as well so let's
go into there are at least two ways this
kubernetes can work it can share the
same IP
ranges as the host Network or it can
have an overlay with a completely
separate IP range could you talk about
how those two work and what's the
difference between them yeah so you can
have I think celium calls it a direct
routing mode and VPC cni so in AWS it
runs very similar to what you're talking
about is that the Pod cider rain
is so that's the IP address ranges that
get assigned to pods running on the
network run along our routed the same
way that a hose network is so everybody
knows how to reach those pods without
having to do any other layer of
abstraction with something like vxlan
that gets encapsulated and it gets
shared between the host over that
encapsulation tunnel so that VX land
tunnel so it's a another layer of
abstraction um from that perspective
you'll get a little bit of a performance
hit cuz you are doing extra packet
encapsulation and sharing that over UDP
between hosts so it all depends again
what you need from that perspective so
if you have issues with if you have IP
address issues like the space VX land
could be helpful from that perspective
but if you could I would use direct
routing from that perspective there's
one less layer to worry about the choice
of those two would be determined by
something you just mentioned which is
the cni and syum being an example say
more about what the cni is so the cni is
a project that helps abstract all of the
networking stuff that we're talking
about so adding deleting updating the
host networks the IP addresses all of
that so when we think about
kubernetes as a whole kubernetes is made
up of a collection of software that
works together and even the container
runtime is another piece of software so
the container runtime interface has a
specification the kubernetes or the
container network interface has a
specification that people Implement that
projects Implement cium is one of them
there's others out there flannel AWS all
the major Cloud providers have their own
cni for working on their Cloud networks
even storage has a runtime a storage
interface so all of these collections of
software talk to each other to enable
the distributed system that is
kubernetes so when a pod comes up
there's another piece of software that's
running on there that's the cuet the
cubit's going to say hey I need to run
this pod and it does that by having a
conversation with the cni and so you can
have a cni installed that will do
specific things for you and celium is
one of those in kubernetes it's really a
control plane and when it needs to do
something it's pretty agnostic about how
it's going to happen it says I need
storage I need networking I need a
container and then it delegates to one
of these interfaces that knows how to do
that on the specific infrastructure
where it's running is that more or less
what you said that is a much more
succinct way of saying what what I just
said yeah okay great now if I'm running
a managed kubernetes on one of the major
Cloud providers I'm going to assume that
cloud provider is opinionated on I
should use their recommended or their
branded
cnii that works with their
networking versus if I'm standing up a
kubernetes cluster that I'm going to
manage then I have to choose the cni is
that so far correct yes yes but it is
also changing so again I have the most
experience with celium so celium is an
approved cni that can run on those
clouds soyum has Partnerships with AWS
Azure and gcp to run those and actually
I think open source celium on gke v data
plane V2 default is celium so there are
use cases where you can just use the
celium
or the celium project versus like the
default like on AWS VPC cni we do need
to disclose cium open source and do you
have any employment relationship with
celium we need to disclose that yeah no
worries so celium is an open source
project it is in the
cncf and we do have an Enterprise
version that customers can pay for so
they get a plethora of other features
outside of just the celium open source
and they get folks like me to help them
with their implementations and support
great now in standing up kubernetes
cluster if there are more than one cnis
that could work in that environment what
are some considerations that go into
selecting the one that you will run it's
always around the use case so in that
time frame we were talking about it I
also used to be a consultant so really
it's what's the use case what do you
need to do so there are certain features
and functionality that are available in
cnis one of the examples we always talk
about is Network policies so another
thing to discuss and talk about all pods
can communicate with other pods that's
one of the pieces of the networking
philosophy in kubernetes the problem
with that is a security aspect so there
is no default Network policy that's
running in there so if you want to
restrict
who can talk to who on the network in a
KU entities cluster you have to use a
cni that supports Network policies so
that's one of the base things you should
look at from that perspective and what I
was talking about cium supports that
there are others Calico the AWS vpcc and
I I think you can do the security groups
at the Pod level as well so things like
that but that's one of the ones you can
look at so there are other Advanced
features and functionality so if you
want to be able to support a service
mesh some of the cnis can support a
service mesh from that perspective so it
it really just depends on what your use
cases are and the functionality that you
desire we had a earlier episode I'll put
in the show notes about service mesh
that can be implemented in a side car
that runs as a container inside a pod it
sounds like you have some options as far
as what layer do you want that
functionality to exist at and maybe it
started out as its own pod but if you
know that you want to do it when you set
up the cluster it may have a better home
in the networking layer so yeah sdo does
use a side car proxy with Envoy I think
they have a new Mode called ambient mode
that doesn't use a sidecar proxy but
celium doesn't use a sidec car proxy he
uses epbf to do that routing for you for
this service smesh routing okay so let's
get into a bit more about the IPS and
routing in the flat model pod uses same
IP ranges as the host network but how
does routing from pod to pod occur
because the network interfaces would not
have the Pod addresses so how how does
routing occur in the flat model so we
have to look at it from a podt pod
perspective pod on the same host host
and then pod on a different host so
again I'll go with the example that I'm
aware of so celium when it runs it knows
what pod IP address ranges are running
where and it installs those routes on
the hosts for you so if you're talking
to like
10.1 from one host and your pods the
destination is 10 to on a different node
it's going to do that routing for you so
it will have the routes installed on
there and it will route that traffic for
you if it's on the same pod it won't
leave the host so if the pods are on the
same host it won't leave that so it has
that connection so it knows that it's on
that bridge on that host so it'll just
direct it to the pod that's on that host
so it just depends on if it's on the
same host or on a different host on the
same host the Pod wants to communicate
with another pod it goes through an
internal networking data structure
called a bridge it doesn't need to go
out on the host Network yeah this is
where we start getting into the
conversation of uh it's it's easy when
we can draw pictures on this but yeah so
that's part of everything that gets set
up from the cn's perspective is that the
network namespace gets created the
ethernet devices in that Network
namespace get created and they get wired
up on the host that bridge Network so
that's how the communication between the
network pod name namespace and the
network host namespace is through that
bridge interface that you were talking
about okay now let's do the case where a
pod wants to talk to a pod which is on
another host the Pod is in a network
name space it has a route it says go to
this network interface in the name space
and now somehow that has to cross the
host
Network and get delivered to a pod on
another node can you walk through some
of those steps yeah so pod a is sitting
on host a and it wants to talk to pod B
on host B so when it's going to set that
Source IP as itself the Pod a the
destination is going to be pod B so when
it goes out that bridge it's going to
understand that it's on a different
network and it's going to have to go
either out of default gateway and
communicate to the host to understand
where it needs to go or like I said in
the case those routes are installed
on the host so it knows where to send
those out and how to how to route those
so again this is where we get into the
cni either can manage things for you or
the underlying hosts have to be able to
have to be able to communicate to each
other so in the ceiling perspective it
knows to reach pod B it needs to set the
destination of that node B because the
routes are there from that perspective
the node B it has an IP address that's
not necessarily in the host Network or
it doesn't belong to the host's main
network interface the thing that tells
it which host to go to is there's a
route to pod B's IP that says go out on
this network something like that MH
okay now if I start up a node completely
unrelated to kubernetes I start up a
Linux VM it has a default name space
it'll be given some routes to Route
things on its local network or its
VPC with kubernetes you now need to add
a bunch of additional routes to manage
the Pod Network Linux offers some
different kernel or programmable
extension points
to allow you to do this you mentioned
ebpf what are some of the tooling that
enables kubernetes to manage these
routes on a default installation it's
going to use IP tables so it will set up
the routing and manage the routing using
IP tables that's one of the other pieces
of Technology besides
epbf okay what are some differences
between IP tables and
ebpf so epbf maybe I'll start explaining
that from that perspective so what epbf
does I think the the
overarching phrase that everyone uses is
that it's JavaScript for the Linux
kernel so it will do what JavaScript did
for HTML it does for the Linux kernel so
normally when you have to make changes
or you want to run something inside of
the kernel you have to create a kernel
module and you have to recompile the
kernel and it's a lot of effort from
that perspective so what epbf did is it
allowed us to create hook points into
the kernel so I can write some C code I
can run it through What's called the BPF
verifier and then I can hook into
specific points in the kernel and
understand I can make those changes
without having to go through that whole
Loop of running a kernel module and so
that's what celium will do for you or
any cni that is running with EPV under
the hood so it generates and creates all
of those hook points in the kernel and
allows you to make those changes in the
routing table intercepting packets
things like that from that perspective
that's how that works from the epbf
perspective and then from an IP table's
perspective there are lots of rules and
that gets very complicated from a
chaining perspective and working through
how that all works is probably not great
for uh communicating without uh we can
put a really nice chart of how all that
works from a a pre- routing and a nap
perspective and it it can if if you ever
look at an IP tables rule set on a
kubernetes node it's a lot the answer to
this might be it depends but in uh
kubernetes network if you did look at
the IP tables rule set how many IP
tables rules would you
see it is linear with the amount of
service and endpoints that you're
running so with services and endpoints
we have to be able to map those pods to
services and be able to Route all of
that and we have to have chains for all
of those one of the value propositions
of kubernetes is your host Network can
scale up or down and another is the
scheduler can spin up or relocate
services on the network to achieve
optimal utilization or to recover from
failures let's say that a new node joins
the host Network what kind of Route
adjustments need to be made on all the
other nodes to incorporate that so
that's one of the scaling issues of Ip
tables is that when you make a change
when you add a new node all of those
rules have to be propagated to that new
node or you know when you make a change
to a service you have to update all of
those endpoints across the entire
cluster from that perspective and it can
get from a performance perspective not
great I don't have the actual numbers in
front of me there's there's lots of
papers out there that talk about the
performance impact of large clusters and
large change sets on IP tables versus
epbf so performance is certainly one of
the aspects of why folks are migrating
to it are we talking with IP tables then
seconds minutes how long to get all the
IP tables
rules you put me on the spot on that one
I mean it can take time uh noticeable
amount of time there two parts here and
I'm not completely sure which one we're
talking about you bring the new node
into the host cluster that new node
needs to have its own IP tables or ebpf
rule set so it can route to the other
nodes and then the entire rest of the
network needs to have at least a few
rules added to route to the new node
which of those is more impactful or
takes long
I wouldn't have a direct answer for you
as being a dynamic nature so a new
node's going to come up kubernetes is
going to do that Balancing Act for you
so it's going to shift workloads to that
new node and then everything has to be
refactored from that perspective and
there's a point I want to make sure if
I've understood this correctly the Pod
does run in its own network name space
are these routing rules added on a per
name space basis so each pod might have
a slightly different set of
routes yeah okay and then maybe we get
now what parts of kubernetes are
interacting with the name spaces and the
kernel extension routing
scripts that's going to
be the QBE proxy and or the container
network interface so as the things are
changing we're watching the end points
we're watching the pods come up and down
and those are the two pieces that are
mostly responsible for that so we
haven't talked about the CBE proxy what
is that the cube proxy again like we
talked about the Kuan project it has
lots of different pieces of software and
Q proxy is one of them and it runs on
each node and it helps Define all of
those pieces so if you say I have this
service with these endpoints it's going
to set up and run those IP tables rules
for you and set all of those up for you
so that's the piece that's watching all
of the watching all of that the CN acni
can do that and there are some that
replace the Q proxy Al together it has a
word proxy in its name is it anything
like other things called proxy like
reverse proxies that we run in front of
a cluster it is the network proxy so
it's the one that's again setting up all
of those IP tables rules and making sure
that everything's available from that
perspective so yeah it's proxying all of
the pods to services communication or
all of the communication in the cluster
and that's a per node or a per pod
cardinality uh
yes because it's running the key proxy
running on each node just like a cni was
running on each node so there's specific
software that runs on all of the nodes
for that perspective and Q proxy is one
of them but it is managing the services
and the endpoints for all of the pods
and deployments and services so that's
why I answered the yes to your question
there's another part of the control
plane we've n yet talked about that
plays role networking the cuet explain
what that is the cuet has two main roles
so the KE blet on a host is the one that
is watching when the Pod gets to it it's
going to start up that pod and Kickstart
all of the other things that we've
talked about but the keylet also does
health checks so if you have health
checks defined in your pod spec it's the
one that's going to be running those
checks for you so that you make sure
that the pods are healthy when you're up
and running at what point when the pods
being started up is it given an IP
address and by who or what that's the
interplay so the cuet is the one that
has the communication with the cni so
the container network interface so the a
pod gets scheduled CU kick starts the
process and asks the cni for an IP
address and to create that interface in
the namespace and the cni based on how
the network is architected it has chunks
or ranges of IP addresses that it knows
are safe to hand out to a particular
node something like that yeah so when
you start up a kubernetes cluster it
asks for what that range is and then it
carves up that range for all of the
nodes in the cluster so depending on how
big the Pod range is will depend on how
many nodes can run in the cluster you
can look at something like the AWS VPC
cni where it actually has math set up so
saying that depending on the Node size
will depend on how many pods you can run
on the cluster so an M5 large can run 30
PS I think it's 29 pods so if you want
to run more than 29 pods because of that
restriction on the networking on the
host then you have to run a larger
instance so there's things like that so
when you're architecting a kubernetes
cluster the network size does matter for
the size of the cluster are there
decisions you could make about IP ranges
or network size that might turn out
later to be not great decisions but are
quite difficult to revert if you don't
like them yeah so there are some things
like if you have pods that you want to
communicate across different clusters
they have to have a distinct pod IP
address range so there are issues from
that perspective again the sizing is an
issue but there are other tricks I keep
talking about AWS because that's the one
I have the most familiarity with for the
past few years so on eks you can add
secondary ranges now you can also
increase the VPC you can add another
range to the VPC and then you can add
another range to the Pod Sider ranges so
you can they allow you to do things like
that so if you maybe properly scaled the
cluster from a instant size perspective
but not the IP address ranges there are
some tricks you can do after the fact
but it does require some planning
especially when you're doing
multi-tenant or you're doing multi
cluster and having communication across
clusters so from a networking
perspective you still have to do what I
would consider like traditional Network
architecting making sure you have the
Pod IP address ranges properly set up
especially if you're doing the flat
networking that we've talked about in
vpcs VPC design in general like if
you're going to peer vpcs they can't
have overlapping ranges so there's lots
of discussion so I think the traditional
networking engineering skills are still
there from even in a cloud native and a
kubet cluster perspective you may be
involved D in different planning
circumstances then based on for cost
reasons you want some pretty large
machines but you have a very small type
of pod so you're going to be running
lots of PODS per Machine versus you have
some really memory intensive service
where you're going to dedicate an entire
machine to that and those type of
considerations would figure into how
large your IP ranges need to be am I
going more or less in the right
direction with that yeah the I mean I
have customers who are running machine
workloads on kinetes where it it is a
single pod running on a single node and
there's also networking tools that would
like Ingress enginex or any Ingress
controller you can have running on an
individual node so again lots of
planning that's involved based on use
cases and what workloads you're going to
be running on the cluster again
conversations with the platform team or
with whatever teams managing your cloud
and kuber's
clusters okay there's another kubernetes
resource that is very tightly tied to
the network you've mentioned a few times
the idea of a service which you might
not know that that's a kubernetes
resource when you hear it because the
word service is so ubiquitous in this
type of engineering there is a
particular thing called a
service what is that so this is again
one of those things where it's a
kubernetes abstraction but it's still
very similar to a networking so you can
think of a service as a virtual IP that
remains that is stateful so it stays
with the service so when you spin up a
service you'll get an IP address that's
routable in the cluster the entire
cluster which is essentially just IP
tables rules that get put across the
cluster but the the issue that it solves
is that pods are ephemeral and pods can
scale as needed right kubernetes is a
dynamic system there's controllers that
are managing how many pods need to be
running in the system so if a pod goes
down for whatever reason it'll bring up
a pod with a different IP address
because it's on a different node
different pod IP address range and so
that changes and that makes things
difficult from a DNS and a client
perspective so to help with that
kubernetes has its abstraction of a
service that has a single IP address
that routes to all of the pods that does
load balancing in the cluster to those
pods so you can hit that service
endpoint and not worry about the Pod IP
addresses changing from that perspective
for example then say in my cluster we
have a product catalog service that's
more intensively used some time of day
than others because more people are
shopping during daytime hours kubernetes
will scale those up or down yet all the
clients in kubernetes that want to talk
to that service will see that single IP
and then that will get routed to one of
the pods that is supporting that service
did I get that right yeah that is one
use case I do want to mention though
that pod Auto scaling is also just
another piece of software that monitors
that from that perspective so everything
is a controller everything's a piece of
software that has its own individual use
cases and go a bit more into how this
single IP address acts as a load
balancing abstraction to multiple pods
yeah so if you see there's a
configuration option when you start up a
Kubin cluster that's the service cider
range and so that's the IP address range
that's going to be used for the services
and on the back end that's IP tables
rules that are set up across all of the
nodes and the cluster so if you want to
route something when you create a
service it gets an IP address the Q
proxy or the cni whichever one's
responsible for all of that sets up
either the IP tables rules or the epbf
routing rules whichever is the backend
technology that CN is using so all of
that gets set up for you automatically
based on those on those softwares so
when a new pod comes up from a Services
perspective we use things called labels
and selectors so you label a pod say
this is app Fu and I have service that
is watching for pods that come up with
app Fu so when those labels and
selectors match it updates it creates an
endpoint and those endpoints get updated
across the cluster saying if you want to
reach one of these here's the IP address
of one of those that matches it is this
an instance of a thing we talked about a
bit earlier that when a new pod joins a
service that potentially every single
node now is impacted because it may need
to add a new route that's part of it
yeah the routing to the service IP will
it load balance at the node level or
does it take into account that there
might be four PODS of the same type
running on a very large node and that
really should count as four rather than
one you're asking a very good question I
think it is I think it does take in
account the number of pods are in there
and I think it does equal path load
balancing I I don't think you can really
change that on an IP tables perspective
but I think you can with certain cnis
that use case I'm not 100% on but I know
that it does take in account all of the
pods that are in the cluster and then
that also brings into account some of
the other things like external traffic
policy so one of the big
issues when you're using kubernetes is
understanding the client IP when it
comes in so when we do the routing the
source net so the source IP address
changes because of the routing that
happens on the cluster so we lose the
client's IP from that perspective so you
can do something with a service by
setting up an external traffic policy
and say it's either cluster-wide or it's
local the problem with local is that if
a service isn't running if pod isn't
running on the
Node then it will drop that traffic so
you'll have some issues with that but
you'll still get the client because it
won't do the extra hop so you know you
have 50 nodes on the cluster you have 10
pods running if you hit one of those
nodes where it's not running and your
external traffic policy is set to local
it drops the traffic so you have to make
some decisions from that perspective
there are other ways to get the client
IP from that perspective and that gets
into the one of the use cases we didn't
get a chance to talk about with Ingress
controllers or load balancers I'm not
sure I understand this last example so
what is the need for the receiving node
to have the client IP for whatever
reason that the application wants to
track what the client IP is and did I
understand correctly that the route from
the services cluster wide IP might route
to a node which does not have an
instance of that service on it yeah it
could so it's going to send it to it's
going to send it to a node because the
IP tables rules are set up across all of
the pods so I can hit a node and it gets
routed to another node that has that pod
running on it and that's when you set it
up as like cluster external network
external policy so if you have it set
the local it's only going to try to
access the pod that's running locally to
that node and if it's not you'll you'll
lose that traffic okay I wanted to talk
a bit about
DNS does the service resource interact
with the DNS in the kubernetes cluster
yes so each service gets a DNS name in
the cluster from that perspective so you
can look up you can do a look up so if
it's I think it's service name.
namespace do cluster. looc or. default I
can't remember the DNS DNS name but that
does map to the service IP address so
we've covered a lot of how it works I
wanted to talk about something you
mentioned right at the top which is that
it's really often the Network's fault to
where you might blame the network first
could you give a troubleshooting
experience you had on a kubernetes
cluster that did turn out to be
something to do with the network how did
you diagnose it and how did you resolve
it one of my favorite tools is a
container called netsh Shoot so netsh
shoot has a lot of networking
troubleshooting tools that you would
expect to have so TCP dump curl all of
those ones that allow you to do all of
the things that you need to help
troubleshoot that so you can start up
that pod and then you can start
diagnosing what the issues are if it's
DNS issue can I you know can I do a ex
internal DNS lookup or can I do an
external DNS lookup um things like that
from that perspective there's also a
really cool tool to help diagnose and
just look at network connectivity and
it's called gold Pinger I think it's by
the Bloomberg group yeah it's it's a
great name but what it does is it sets
up a Damon set and a Damon set sets up a
pod on every node in the cluster and
then they all start talking to each
other and they start pinging each other
and then you can have like a graph UI
and you can see where there's
connectivity issues in the cluster so
between those two pieces of software I
like to use those to help troubleshoot
issues I haven't really had a chance to
use the eeral pods that just came I
think they just came GA maybe 128 129 I
can't remember but you can attach like a
network pod to drist pods that don't
have a shell and things like that
haven't had a chance to use use those
but that would be really helpful from
that perspective and the last one that
we did that I looked at is that the cuet
kept killing a pod off but when we got
into the host and we were looking around
what had happened is when we T remember
when we talked about the cubet we'll use
the routing rules that are on the Node
to try to reach the Pod to check the
liveliness probes the Readiness probes
well somebody had created a host
interface with the same IP address as a
pod and it's going to favor the local
connected ones over the one that's
connected via an Ethernet a vth pair so
it was trying to route to that Local
Host interface and it's not running Port
80 it wasn't running anything so it's
just again I I liken it to it's still
normal networking troubleshooting from
that perspective what can I reach how
far can I go out what's the latency look
like what a still trying to go through
the normal networking troubleshooting
with the little extra of the kubernetes
abstractions that we've talked about
today that is a great example that
reminds me of another question I wanted
to ask if I bring up any kind of
workload on one of the major Cloud
providers they're going to provide a lot
of metrics and dashboards of their VMS
and their Network I could see traffic
Ingress and egress volumes on a per VM
basis
now if you're running kubernetes do you
need to build or add in something that
will monitor the kubernetes networking
abstractions and and why would you do
that and what would you be looking for
yeah I mean pods are still using
resources as needed so you probably
you'll still want to monitor those
resources there are tools that allow you
to do that like Prometheus you can do
pod metrics monitoring from that
perspective and you can shell those out
to things like cloudwatch I think eks
has some I think it's called container
insights they have metrics that you can
look at to monitor your pods from that
perspective there's other tools as well
traditional monitoring tools I know like
data dog has a container plugins that
allow you to monitor those as well so
there are what people would consider
again like traditional monitoring tools
that have adapted to be able to run in a
container world can you give an example
of something that might get lost if you
only could see network aggregated up to
the VM level but you might be able to
see it when you have the resolution down
to the Pod level one of the things that
gets lost is that container context so
containers are just processes running on
a host so you'll see a host Spike
Network traffic but you won't know why
maybe you'll just see the process ID of
those things but you won't be able it
takes a lot of work to correlate that
process ID to a container that's running
and to an application team that maybe
just did a new deployment that had a
memory leak so having tools that are
container aware is very helpful from
that perspective to allow you to monitor
pods and processes from that perspective
so yeah you'll lose a lot of context
where you'll just see 50 50 process
proces that and then you'll have to do
the mapping manually and nobody wants to
do that we're getting close to end of
time here I mentioned your book at the
top I understand a second edition is
being discussed or prepared what would
be in the second edition that readers
could look forward to yeah so kubernetes
and networking it is for folks that are
an entry level I would say I say it's a
layered approach because we start with
talking about just normal networking and
then we build up to running the Linux
networking that we just talked about to
running on a cloud provider with C A
manage service and I think it was
released about two years ago so things
like Gateway API hadn't been GA yet
that's probably the big one in there
from that perspective I have a whole
list of it that I've sent to my provider
we'll probably talk a lot more about
epbf there was a short stint in there
from that from that chapter we did a
huge Focus I think on chapter 2 was just
all walking through that IP tables
example that we talked about like how
those get set up how they get mapped to
services and endpoints I think the bulk
of chapter 2 was just on IP table so
we'll probably downplay that and migrate
more into talking about epbf from that
perspective those are the two off the
top of my head that I can remember and
then always just updating the examples
and things like that probably adding a
troubleshooting section cuz we didn't
really have a lot of shooting from that
perspective and we will link to some of
those tools you mentioned in the show
notes is there any place you'd like
listeners to go where they can find you
I am strong Jay-Z on most platforms so
the kubernetes and the cncf slack GitHub
if you have an issue with the Ingress
engine x controller which I help
maintain please come to our community
meetings every Thursday at 11: Eastern
we have more information about that in
the kubernetes slack in the Ingress
engine X users Channel I hang out there
to help answer support questions
anything like that James thank you very
much for speaking to software
engineering radio thank you it's been
lots of fun this has been Robert bluman
and thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening